where I only pushed it once, and I thought it was recording, and I did a five-hour interview.
None of it was recorded.
Yeah.
So today is May 8, 2026.
My name is Caitlin Sheets, and I am here with Dr. G. Cliff Lamb.
We're conducting this interview in the Ag Life Science Building on the campus of Texas A&M University in College Station, Texas.
The interview is part of an oral history project documenting the experiences of Aggies for the 150th celebration of Texas A&M.
Do I have consent to record this?
Yes.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Thank you for sharing your story with me.
To begin, can you give us a little brief bio kind of information about where you're born, where you grew up, that type of thing?
Sure.
Yeah.
So, yeah, thanks a lot for taking the time to chat.
So I have a very unique background.
I actually grew up in Zimbabwe, Africa.
Wow.
So South Central Africa on a beef, cattle, dairy, corn and tobacco operation.
How interesting.
So throughout my whole career.
I was very interested in agriculture.
I knew at a very young age I was going to come to the U.S. and study.
And so in the late 80s, I came and I studied at Middle Tennessee State University, got my bachelor's degree, and then went to Kansas State and got my master's and PhD.
I've always been highly passionate in reproductive biology.
and using reproduction to increase efficiency of livestock operations yeah so so that's uh that was my uh formal education and then from there i had full intentions to go back to africa at that point that was always my goal and in the late 1990s early 2000s there was a big uh push by the government of zimbabwe to nationalize
all of the farms and ranches so basically um the operation i grew up on and many of the operations uh those operations were nationalized and so there was not a real large incentive for me to return to africa because didn't really have anything that we could sort of take over and and operate and so i took a position at the university of minnesota as a faculty member
I spent 10 years as a faculty member at the University of Minnesota and loved it.
Really enjoyed being there.
Following that, I was asked to essentially do some work as an administrator and a faculty member at the University of Florida, and I was there for about 10 years.
Wow.
I'm in my 10th year now at Texas A&M.
I came here as the department head in March of 2017 as department head of animal science.
I spent five years as department head of animal science.
and also interim department head for ecology and conservation biology and other departments on campus.
At that time, that department was restructured with wildlife and fisheries into two separate departments, and I served as the interim department head for rangeland wildlife and fisheries management.
at the same time as being department head of animal science.
It's a lot of work.
Yeah, it sure is.
But a great experience.
And then in December of 2021, the chancellor...
of the Texas A&M University System had called me and asked me if I would be interested in being the director of AgriLife Research.
And so I saw a lot of opportunity, a lot of opportunity to grow our agency and took that position.
And I've been in this role since
January of 2022.
Fabulous.
Many roles and much experience.
For someone who is ignorant, going back a little bit on what you're talking about, what does it mean when they took the farms, the ranches and made it state?
Yeah, so they nationalized about 6,000 farms and ranches.
In other words, the government took them away from the landowners.
Most people whose farms were taken, they had about 90 days to leave the land.
And then they basically...
uh redistributed the land to other people either people from the city or uh government officials received land wow how disruptive hugely disruptive uh and really what it did zimbabwe for people who don't know was had the reputation uh the name of being the bread bread basket of africa um so we were producing
enough food to feed the whole country and we exported a ton of food to neighboring countries and within three years we were producing less than 20 percent of the food that we were producing three years before as a result of the nationalization and Zimbabwe's economy at the time was largely driven on agriculture and the economy imploded to the point that inflation was so bad
That it was over 175% a day, inflation-wise.
Oh, wow.
It was a real disaster.
So basically the country went bankrupt.
Yeah.
Thank you for the history.
Listen, that is out.
Out to the people who... Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
Sorry, just digesting that.
So you said you were always interested in cattle and reproductive aspect of it.
What kind of drew you to that?
So growing up on a fairly large ranch and farm, we both were farmed and ranched.
And so we had dairy cattle and we had beef cattle.
And from a very young age,
um i'm not sure what it was that drew me to specifically reproduction in cattle um i was highly passionate about um about livestock i mean from a very very young age as early as i can remember i just loved working on the farm but uh we had a neighbor that was one of the only people in the country who did
embryo transfer and embryo transfer is basically taking embryos from genetically superior animals and take causing that cow to produce more than she normally does and then taking those embryos and transferring them
to surrogates or recipients that are not as genetically good, but they give birth to a genetically superior animal.
So I used to just, I loved, I mean, when he was doing it on our farm, it just sort of captured my attention.
And when I was in elementary school, in fact, nobody in my family can remember me ever not talking about
specializing in reproduction.
My whole life, that's what I was just passionate about.
And so throughout high school, I learned to artificially inseminate cows at a very young age.
I was in high school, very early in high school, and very fortunate to have had the opportunity then to specialize in that through my career as a researcher.
That's absolutely fascinating that it's not just that you're interested in cattle, but this is a very specific part of the cattle too.
So, wow.
What do you to specifically the academic and research side of things rather than the industry side of things?
Really good question.
To be perfectly honest, my goal after I got a PhD was to return and use the skills that I developed
in growing agriculture back in Zimbabwe.
And that was to not only improve production efficiency of cattle operations, beef cattle or dairy operations, but I also had a passion in wildlife.
And so potentially utilizing the skills that I'd learned to then do some conservation work.
So preserving genetics of endangered species and things like that.
When I got word that I was not going to be able to go back and do anything on the farm or ranch, I sort of had a choice to either go into the U.S. industry on the commercial side, working with either a pharmaceutical company or a nutrition company or working in the industry somewhere or starting my own company.
or to go into research and while i was working on my phd i became really intrigued it was a very interesting time of year for where for for where i had an interest and we were at that time developing a system to inseminate cows
where we did not have to know when they were in heat.
So we called it fixed-timed artificial insemination.
So you take a group of cows, and typically you would have to make sure that the cow was receptive to become pregnant, right?
She'd be in heat.
And so if you had, say, 100 cows,
If you wanted to get them all pregnant, you go out there and watch them and see when they come in heat, then you artificially inseminate them.
We were in the process at that time of developing a system where you could inseminate them all at the same time on the same day, and it just makes things more efficient for a producer.
So we started working on that while I was in my PhD, and I thought, you know, this is an opportunity to have a significant global impact in production systems for beef cattle where you can use reproduction to improve production efficiency of cattle operations.
And so the first 10 years of my research career, that really was my primary focus, is refining that system, working on products that were not approved in this country at the time, working to get them approved so that cattle producers had access to those products, and then being able to refine it.
excuse me, refine it in such a way that it was efficient for cattle producers to use.
And, you know, you go through this process when you're working on your master's and PhD, that when you first start your master's, you really don't understand what research is, to when I finish my PhD,
I was really intrigued by the scientific method, the process, understanding all of the things that have been done, and then coming up with ideas to make a difference in the future.
By the time I finished my PhD, I could see myself in a role.
You're knee-deep in it.
Exactly.
Is that system still in use today?
Absolutely.
So I'll give you some examples.
When we started, so between 1997 and 2003 is sort of when we really developed and refined these systems, more than half of the cows that are artificially inseminated in the U.S. today are
use the system we developed in 2003 and so that is happening today and we also in 2002 we started what's called the beef reproduction task force and so to the scientists who work in this space around the country a few of us got together to start the task force and
we came up with a set of recommendations for beef producers to use on what systems to use to get their cows pregnant to artificial insemination.
About half of the protocols that are on that sheet were ones that we played
we developed or played a major role in developing.
And so in the U.S., very, very fortunate that about 65 to 70 percent of all the heifers that are inseminated right now use a protocol that we had a hand in developing in some way.
And then more than 50 percent of the cows.
That's so impressive.
Yeah.
Globally, I think that's even is where we might have even had a greater role.
And so you take a look and 2002, 2003 was the first time I visited Brazil.
And Brazil obviously is the next largest beef producer in the world behind the US.
And we started talking about using these systems to get cows pregnant in Brazil.
At the time, less than a million cows in Brazil were artificially inseminated through fixed-timed artificial insemination.
Today, about 18 million.
every year are inseminated using a system or a variation of a system we developed in the late 90s and early 2000s so yeah yeah so huge impact there in australia about 75 percent of beef cattle producers that are inseminated use the system we developed
So this is a global kind of impact.
That is so impressive.
What are some things that you've, like new things added to it that you've seen in the years?
Yeah.
So, you know, like I said, in those first 10 years, sort of 97 to 2007, we spent a lot of time refining these systems.
And I've continued to work in that space to even refine things a little bit further.
But we've had the advent of...
the development of new technologies that then we incorporate into those types of systems.
I'll give you one example.
And very close to us here in Navasota is sexing technologies.
It's a company that has a technology that can sex semen.
And so you can inseminate a cow and the cow will give birth to over 90% accuracy that cow will give birth to a calf that is of a desired sex.
So we took the systems we developed and developed fixed time AI systems where you could use sex semen.
because most of the system we developed with conventional semen, and those two products are very different in the way that they're utilized.
I didn't know that's possible.
It's like science fiction, futuristic to me.
It is, yes.
Yeah, exactly.
And then obviously I have big interests in other reproductive technologies, and so I've done a lot of work in in vitro fertilization,
a little bit in cloning and it's an area that excites me right now and i have graduate students and postdoc students right now that are working on we call it precision genetics so it's using crisper cas9 which is a gene editing technology to try and create animals
that are more productive I mean we have calves on the ground right now that have been edited for the slick gene and so just to explain how that works is that the slick gene is basically
it's a prolactin receptor prolactin is used for milk is used for milk right it's a hormone that stimulates milk production but at the same time it's also tied to uh to animals that have about 10 of the hair of their normal of the normal kind and so we've edited those animals
to have the slick gene so they have 10% of the hair of their full siblings.
So full sibling, two brothers or two sisters can be standing side by side, and the one that's been edited for the slick gene has only 10% of the hair of the other one.
And why is that important?
Well, it's important because in Texas it's really hot.
And so if they have less hair, they don't spend as much energy trying to cool down during the warm times of the year.
That's so fascinating.
When we take the temperature of these animals during the heat of the day, those animals that have this slick gene have a body temperature that's about a degree to a degree and a half less.
in the middle of the day than those that have full hair that are full siblings so for warm climates you can ultimately breed these animals and they are more productive they survive better they get they're not as sick there's just a lot of these traits that will help them be more productive and so
How creative.
My first thoughts when I think of science and reproduction, I don't think creative, but that is so creative.
That's right.
Yeah, it is.
So that's a simple gene to edit, and obviously that's where we are right now.
You can do an edit to make animals not have horns.
And so the reason that you would do that right now in the old days, cows needed horns to fight off predators.
We really don't have to worry about that now.
Right.
But so what a lot of people do is they actually have to dehorn the animals manually, which becomes it's just not a nice procedure.
But if we breed them to not have horns, then you don't even have to do that.
Yeah.
Right.
yeah but my ultimate goal is to try and create edits that are multi
that sort of focuses on more than one gene and focus really on the disease side of things.
And the reason for that is that I want cattle to, I want to be able to breed animals that are resistant to certain diseases or ailments that you don't have to treat.
So you think of what happens then.
They're more productive because they don't get sick.
Fewer of them die, fewer of them get sick, and so on.
But in addition to that is we have a significant reduction in the use of antibiotics.
And, you know, there's a lot of discussion about antibiotic resistance, right?
Right, right.
And so how do we limit the use of antibiotics in animal agriculture?
And this is one way that I see as a potential solution.
That's so smart.
As you said, two solutions right there, or two problems, one solution.
One solution, yeah, exactly.
Is there any things that you can share that your protégés are working on?
Anything you're... Yeah.
I mean, so right now we have graduate students that are working in
anywhere from the really applied side of things and when i say applied it's things that are immediately applicable to a producer right so our results might have application to them this year or next year right and then we have some very fundamental things that you know results might only help us in 10 or 15 years from now so i'll give you an example
of something that we're working on in the short term and that is utilizing different products to give to cows around the start of the breeding season so we're not even worrying about whether they're artificially inseminated because still there are so many cows out
that you can't handle very easily but if you could just have them once what can you do to treat them that they become pregnant sooner in the breeding season and they give birth to their calves sooner in the calving season
and those calves end up becoming a lot more productive than if they don't become pregnant sooner in the breeding season so we're working on a couple of projects in that space then sort of in the intermediate space we have a graduate student right now working on utilizing doing in vitro fertilization
and we're using seminal plasma so when a bull ejaculates semen right there's a lot of it's not just the sperm but there's a lot of fluids around the sperm that has has a lot of components
Well, we have data from multiple bulls that are very high fertility, and we have bulls that are low fertility, right?
And we have all of this data.
And so what we've done is we're collecting seminal plasma from the two groups and then going to see if we can fertilize embryos
and understand what it is about the seminal plasma in those two groups that causes differences in fertility.
Wow.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, it does.
Absolutely.
And then obviously the thing that I talked about is on the gene editing front.
And there are several things that we're working on.
That's very exciting.
A layperson's question.
So the insemination, when you inseminate all of them at once instead of having to wait, does that create a situation where all of them are pregnant, thus give birth at the same time too?
That's a great question.
Yeah.
So gestation of a cow is about 280 to 285 days.
Okay.
so about 10 days longer than a human and so yes they're all pregnant let's say on the same day um and when they go to calve they're usually spread out about at the max about three weeks okay so not unlike humans right so humans give birth 10 days early and some humans give birth 10 days later so that would be very similar in cattle
When we do mass inseminate, you get somewhere around 50 to 60 percent of them pregnant.
So not all of them will get pregnant, you know, and cattle are highly fertile because they've been selected for being fertile, because if they don't produce a calf,
They consume resources, so they're eliminated, right?
Yeah.
So that percentage is very high, 50 to 60 percent for a single offspring bearing species, like a cow that generally only gives birth to one.
They usually only give birth to one animal at a time.
So litters are very different, right?
You can get a pig pregnant almost any time you're inseminator.
You've just got to hope you get more piglets than one or two.
But cows only give birth to one.
In comparison, and I give this, I tell people this all the time.
So 50 to 60% of those cows get pregnant, but humans are about half that.
Fertility.
Humans are the least fertile species that give birth to one animal.
Really?
Yes.
Because we don't select humans for fertility.
True.
And, you know, even in the wild, there's selection for fertility, right?
Right.
But humans, we try to figure out ways that every woman who wants to get pregnant...
We try and get them pregnant in some way.
Right, right.
And so we're a very infertile species.
That really puts it in perspective too.
Yeah.
And think whatever, think everything that they don't give birth all at the same time because that would be a disaster.
It would.
It would truly.
But it is a lot of people don't realize that only about one in three times that
they ovulate, do they act and or obviously through fertilization and things like that.
Only about one in three survive.
Wow.
In humans.
I did not know that either.
People know that.
Yes.
Because a lot of humans don't know that they're pregnant or there's a fertilized egg and the egg dies before they
That makes sense.
Thank you for going to the little nitty-gritties of that.
So, you were in Florida before Texas A&M, you said.
How did the opportunity arrive to you for this original position here?
At Texas A&M?
Yes.
You know, it's a good question.
I'll go back to when I...
There are two sort of things here.
When I was trying to decide where to go to university when I was growing up in Africa, I was very familiar with Texas A&M and Colorado State.
Those are two universities that I was aware of that really did a good job in the reproduction space in the world at the time.
And so I actually applied to those two universities to come to study at that time.
Interesting.
And ended up going to Middle Tennessee State for a very different reason.
So that was my first sort of thought of Texas A&M.
I had no intention of being a university administrator.
Never thought about it.
It was never really something that I was trying to do.
However, when I was at the University of Florida, I was an administrator with a faculty position, and there were several universities that were asking if I'd be interested in being a department in.
I had thought that if I was ever going to do that, the place that I would go and do it was at my alma mater, which was Kansas State, and was considering that because I knew the department head was retiring.
At that time, I did get a call from Texas A&M that said, why don't you come and take a look?
I considered it.
I came and took a look.
And I thought that there's probably no university that has the resources and the desire to be the best.
And so after speaking with my wife and my family, I said, you know,
I'd be crazy not to take the opportunity because I think I could give it the reputation as being the best in the world.
So that's how I came to the decision.
It's so funny to me how things from our past pop up again like that.
You replied to it and it's here again.
Exactly.
Fate.
Yeah, absolutely.
It was fate.
That's right.
So that decision, was that decision made when they brought you out and you saw the facilities and everything like that too?
Yeah, so I think I took four trips out here during the process of when they interviewed me by phone to when I finally took the position.
You know, we had kids that were in high school.
I had to make sure that they were comfortable moving here at the time.
And then at the same time, I wanted to learn more about
what are some of the things that seem to be um should i say slowing them down or not giving them the opportunity to be recognized outside of texas as one of the better yeah animal science departments in the country or the world and you know most of that stuff was probably just decisions oh okay yeah that i thought i could make and yeah and we did
Fantastic.
So when you arrived here, what were your first impressions of the department, as well as just the broader ag life culture?
What am I trying to say?
The College of Agriculture.
So the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences is the college in which the Department of Animal Science sits.
And so it's one of 15 departments.
The things that I, so first arriving in, things that I thought were
were things that they could improve on is fantastic culture, right?
Everybody who graduates from A&M is proud to be from A&M.
And it has this significant impact in their future professions.
And, you know, it's a network.
A lot of people say it's a cult, right?
But it's a very good cult.
It's a nice cult.
There are some things that are just very quirky about Texas A&M that make it unique, which I really enjoy.
However, the one thing that I felt like is that...
that previous decisions in terms of who was hired it tended to be they all tended to have ties to Texas A&M and I felt like the way that Texas A&M is going to grow especially that department is to consciously find the best person out there and it didn't matter where they're from they could be from some other country
It could be from a different state or a different university.
But we needed to broaden the horizon and bring in the best people rather than just saying, we have the best people because we taught them here.
Change the way we think about people, change the way that we teach in the classes.
We revised the curriculum in the department
So shortly after I arrived, and some of the legwork had already been done before I got here, but we pushed it forward where we wanted more hands-on experiences, things like that, having more labs, you know, and it's complicated because...
It's very difficult for a university to have those resources, but we felt it was going to be important for us to have more hands-on opportunities, ensure we had internship opportunities, animal experiences.
Yeah, actually get out of the classroom and into the fields.
Yeah, and learn a little bit more beyond the classroom.
Those were all things we implemented.
How was that received?
Oh, I think, you know, obviously it was received well because the feedback we got in that process said that that's a big need.
The students like the opportunity.
But what they're really...
took to is some of the new faculty members that we brought in that may not have been Aggies brought a different perspective.
Right.
And so we changed the perspective.
So important.
Yeah, exactly.
Do you remember some of those first people that you brought in?
Mm-hmm.
Yes, I do.
Absolutely.
And, you know, it was not easy for many of them to integrate.
Right, yeah.
But, you know, they knew that they had my support.
And I think that that probably helped.
And many of those faculty are thriving.
They were doing extremely well.
That's fantastic that they're still here.
That shows that it worked right there.
Yeah.
Because people don't stay in places that they're not happy.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So what were some key questions that you set out to answer throughout your work?
I mean, we've gone over some of them, but even now for questions for the future.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I can share this in a couple of...
So from my research background, some key questions, which we've talked about, is how do you use reproduction to improve production efficiency?
When we hear people talking about sustainability of agricultural systems today, everybody talks about...
methane and all of these things, right?
And how do you reduce methane in animals?
And there's talks on climate change and the impacts on water and all of those things.
But the number one factor that affects sustainability of livestock operations is getting them pregnant.
And if they're not pregnant, it doesn't matter how much less they consume to produce more or how much less methane or whatever.
They're inefficient, right?
And they're not sustainable.
So using reproduction to increase sustainability of livestock production systems, and we still work on that today.
That's an interesting idea from somebody from the outside that I didn't even think about that the more efficient the production is, reproduction is, the more sustainable it is.
Absolutely.
The common person doesn't put those two things together.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And I feel bad that for some reason people have taken –
cows or ruminants it's not just cows but certainly cows are the big thing but sheep and goats um and said you know they're producing greenhouse gases and getting and really it's such a small part of the total greenhouse gas emissions that even if we got rid of every cow we wouldn't change greenhouse gas emissions by
more than half a percent right yeah and so if you get rid of every cow it's not going to change much yeah unfortunately we're
uh the general population doesn't understand that because 98 98 of the population does not work directly in agriculture in this country correct and we have a social media i mean everybody makes it makes up their mind on very small snippets of things that they get to believe yeah so it's really unfortunate it's no context behind it yeah that makes sense
Yeah.
So, um, you know, questions that I ask now in my role as director of AgriLife Research.
So AgriLife Research is, uh, it's a state agency, uh, within the Texas A&M university system.
You know, we're on the A&M campus, but we don't just support A&M.
We support all 12 universities and, uh, we have, uh, locations all over the state.
um but yeah so questions that really that i really focus on now is how do we continue to figure out ways to produce more food for a growing population of texas on less and less arable land right and texas is particularly different from any other states because 95 of the land in texas is privately owned
I did not know that.
Yeah.
So most other states have more public land than Texas does as a percentage.
And we have about 1,500 people moving into Texas every day.
So that's 1,500 extra mouths we have to feed.
Correct.
The population of Texas is
million right now and 85% of the population is probably urban which leaves about 15% more rural and living in more rural regions of the state but the problem we have is that we had a lot more arable land previously or land for livestock
texas has done very well economically people who live in texas have more resources so they want a little bit more land and so
they are now purchasing arable land.
And you see urban regions that were once land that was producing food on, right?
Oh, no.
And so you see all of this segmentation of land going on in Texas that is just gradually eating away at our arable land that we produce the food to feed the population on.
That's concerning.
It is.
And so...
from my standpoint as director of agri-life research is how do we become even more efficient on less and less land to feed a growing population and then the other thing that we have a major problem with is water so there's competition now and more and more competition for water for people that is taking it away from
the agricultural use water, right?
You take a look at what is happening in the Rio Grande Valley where we've lost an industry like the sugarcane industry is gone because there was not enough water for sugarcane.
You go further up the Rio Grande towards West Texas, El Paso and that region
And a lot of those crops can't be grown that used to be grown.
They're vegetables.
It used to be a huge vegetable area.
We can't grow vegetables because the water has become so brackish.
Yeah, yeah.
They can't put it on the soil, so they can't grow vegetables.
So it's not just cattle, it's all production.
It's all production.
Yeah.
Um, and then you go up into the high plains.
So, uh, where most of the cattle production is.
Um, so this is where the feedlots are.
Uh, Texas is now the third largest dairy state.
So in, in the country and, um,
they get their water largely from the Ogallala Aquifer.
And it's not recharging at the rates it should.
So how's that going to impact agriculture 20, 30, 40 years from now?
And so we're trying to find solutions for that.
have a question um and if you don't want to touch this topic let me know um the first thing that popped in my head when you're talking about limited resources especially water is data centers and the conversation around that and water yeah is there is there a a meeting or a plan kind of thing yeah so you you may not be aware but so within
we have multiple entities that we run.
One entity is called the Texas Water Resource Institute, and it's a statewide effort.
I have a director that reports up to me, and we have these discussions all the time.
So data centers are, you know, there's a lot of discussions about data centers and the use of water.
And then you have the oil and gas industry that is utilizing a lot of, or generating a lot of, it's called produced water.
It's water that is part of the fracking industry, right?
So that's additional water that we are actually getting, but it's not very clean.
You can't drink it, right?
So the discussions we're having right now are...
Can you use some of this water that people can't drink for data centers, for agricultural land, for things like that, so that you save the potable or the drinking water for the human population?
So that's work that's going on right now.
See, that makes me feel better.
That's something I hope gets put out into the public and they hear about that.
Yeah, that's right.
Major concerns, right, with these data centers and storage facilities, right, energy storage facilities, is water is how they are cooled and how do we utilize water in such a way that it doesn't take away from the current needs.
That makes sense.
Thank you.
Can you talk about maybe a project or a finding or something that you feel that's particularly important impact on the production practices here or at large?
Yeah.
Well, maybe I can touch on one that I think is really important that we're trying to resolve.
A lot of people don't realize that Texas has
the largest land ports of entry for agricultural products into the U.S. Really?
So you can go to Brownsville, Laredo, or El Paso.
and agricultural products are coming into the U.S. through Mexico.
And then we've got the seaports on the Gulf, so Corpus Christi, Houston, Galveston.
So you've got all of these agricultural products coming into the U.S. and at any day there could be a pathogen, there could be a disease that comes into the U.S.
that we don't have a solution for and so we spend a lot of time trying to figure out how do we prevent that stuff from being imported because once it gets into texas then it can spread through the rest of the years there's no other state that brings as many and as much agricultural products into the u.s than we do in texas
And so whether it's livestock or crops or vegetables or fruits, whatever it is, there could be a fly on a fruit that comes in.
People don't realize this, but if it gets in and then it spreads, it could destroy some other agricultural industry that we're unaware of.
And so I'll give you some examples.
Right now,
you may have heard of the New World Screwworm.
Yes.
So we're at the forefront of fighting the screwworm.
Our goal is to figure out ways to keep the screwworm from entering the U.S.
Right now, the closest we have a detected screwworm is about 60 miles from the border, but today that could
Panama, all the way up to 60 miles from the U.S. border.
So if the screw room gets here, and you talked about a production practice, right, it will change the way that livestock and wildlife producers produce their product in South Texas.
It will significantly impact them.
you know because basically a screw worm is a female only mates once but she'll plant the egg in an open wound of healthy flesh and then that screw basically the lava is just like a screw and it just drills itself into this live flesh so it's a lot of work yeah um and it usually is a wound so it could be where an animal has a bite or
um there's some infection or some type of laceration or something like that and so on the beef production side when an animal is born where the umbilical cord is is a perfect place for a screw worm or if you have to dehorn an animal take the horns off you create open worms there on the wildlife side which might be worse than on the livestock side is when the males are rutting
um or when they're fighting that's the opportunity for them to significantly have screw up so it's a it's a huge concern but it's going to change agricultural production in texas if it crosses the board absolutely yeah and when it was here 50 60 70 years ago it did not
uh we did not have the wildlife industry we do now most of the landowners in south texas were making a prior making their money primarily from agriculture from raising livestock and selling livestock today it's really difficult just to have a single source of income like livestock and so they either have they make money from the livestock
wildlife and hunting or oil and gas so those three forms in some way i shouldn't say oil and gas it could be renewable energy also so wind solar things like that so there's sort of three forms of income if you think that the screw room gets in here and has an impact on cattle and an impact on wildlife right that's going to be a significant drain on the landowners that could crash absolutely um
Someone from outside of Texas, whenever the screwworm first hit, did you guys ever find out how to deal with it at a mass level?
yeah so and right now as of today but like i said i get an update every week um as of today we don't have screw room in the u.s okay and some some people believe we do but we do not have screw room in the u.s every now and then a human might come back with a screw room or something but but
um population of screw yeah um the way that it was pushed back in the 1950s 60s and 70s is the sterile fly um uh technology so because the screw are a female only makes once
we can use irradiation and so we can irradiate lava before they become flies to be sterile okay yeah and so essentially what was done is basically they irradiated these these lava they became flies they were not sterile and then those were deployed where the screw worms were
and they deployed enough of them that they're overwhelmed just based on numbers right they overwhelm the population of wild screwworm flies and so it was mostly the sterile males mating the females and then they basically wiped them out and pushed them all the way down to mexico
How interesting?
Sorry, down to Panama, through Mexico down to Panama.
But so there were a lot of these plants.
So there was a plant in South Texas, a plant in Mexico, a plant in Nicaragua, a plant in Panama that was producing sterile flies every week.
And that's how they got rid of them.
well what happened is they stopped they closed down all of those facilities except for the one in panama and as the screw room was moving north the panama facility just couldn't produce enough sterile flies that makes sense so so they're building a new facility in texas right now to be able to just in case just yes to be able to help push those flies back so thank you for explaining that to me um yeah
Is there ways your research has changed or evolved over the course of your career as new technologies and new challenges have arrived?
Yeah, so from my standpoint, I'll talk about it from my research and then as an administrator.
So, yeah, there is no question that...
My focus has changed over time as we have, I shouldn't say perfected, but as we've refined processes.
And I talked about fixed-timed artificial insemination.
And I continue to do work in this space.
But the improvements are only incremental, right?
And so I've tried to find other ways to enhance reproductive efficiency, right?
And so one of the areas that's important to me is the only way you can generally increase pregnancy or have more cows give birth is
Yeah.
the genetics side of things.
How can we improve the genetics?
And that's why gene editing and, you know, with the advent and development of CRISPR-Cas9 and the advent of the first clone sheep, Dolly, at the Roslyn Institute in
the UK, that technology has given us a chance to combine those two technologies to generate gene-additive cattle.
So that's pretty cool.
That's so neat.
It makes me excited to see what kind of technology comes out in the future and how that impacts that.
But as an administrator, I think the
you know you go through these phases of where new technologies incrementally change the way you do business right now we are in a phase of if we're going to increase our efficiency of food production
We're in a phase right now where we need to significantly advance our work in the use of artificial intelligence, machine learning, sensor technology, and things like that that develop aids, whether they're decision tools or technologies.
vastly change the way that we do business absolutely yeah so ai is going to change agriculture for the future have you already seen it oh yes okay yeah i've got several great examples right and so um
So we have our big digital ag group at our Corpus Christi Center has developed a model using drones and satellites and big data taking weather and passing future forecast weather data.
And they predicted, this would have been two years ago, that cotton farmers in the region should harvest their cotton three weeks earlier than they ever have done before.
And those that actually did it got a 10% increase in the total cotton value of their crops than they'd ever got before.
One producer didn't believe it, and he harvested his cotton sometime after July 4th is when they do it down there.
And he told me that he said, because he didn't listen,
it was about a $375,000 loss by not doing it.
So there's a tangible example of how artificial intelligence, machine learning, and all of the data science can significantly change.
That could make or break somebody.
Absolutely.
On the animal side, we all walk around with phones.
We walk around with watches that keep track of
heart rate and all of this stuff, you've seen these aura rings that people wear, right?
That are always monitoring something about them, whether it's blood pressure, heart rates, things like that.
um we're starting to use this technology right and it goes back to trying to identify animals that might be sick before they even act sick so yeah traditionally how we would do that is somebody's looking at the animals every day says oh that animal's got droopy ears it looks like it's not healthy we need to go and get its temperature and treat it well we're using this technology now to try and identify animals
that are not doing well before they show clinical signs you can treat them sooner they recover quicker you use less antibiotics you use less treatments and
That way you use, have less production losses.
Right.
Does that make sense?
That absolutely does.
And I know, I mean, I have a Garmin watch, and I'm out there all the time, and I can just tell by...
how my uh the app is telling me it's like oh yeah you didn't sleep that great last night or you may be getting sick because of some some markers right and we're doing that with livestock
I can, all I can picture is the cows wearing little smart watches.
Yeah, so they wear ankle bracelets, like, or some have collars, some have ear tags.
So there's various wearables that we have now for livestock.
There's even a situation where they were working, have you seen these little dog robots?
Mm-hmm.
So one of the big issues in the fed cattle industry right now is some confined animals that are in feedlots just before they go to harvest.
They have what are called pen riders.
And these are people that will ride their horses through these pens every day to check the animals to make sure that they're healthy.
Well, there's a company right now that is using a dog as a robot
that is trained to look for animals that might not be well so that it can replace some of the pen writers because there's just not as many of them out there.
Right.
That is so neat.
The future is now.
The future is now, exactly.
It's so interesting.
Is there anything in your work in particular that you're very proud of and that'll be your shining mark?
You know, I mean, I think that I'm the most proud of is the students that I've trained, right?
I mean, the success that they had, right?
There are some accomplishments that I think will...
uh have long lasting impacts after i'm gone but yeah so certainly i'll say by the students that i've trained especially the graduate students i mean not that i i don't want to minimize the impact on undergraduate students but i i've been very fortunate to have had some phenomenal students that have
If it wasn't for them, I would not have had the career I had.
They're the ones that probably deserve as much credit.
You know, where they've come up with great ideas and I've just figured out a way to facilitate it.
Right.
And so, you know, I've got...
I think I have 10 students that are now faculty members and researchers at universities around the world, anywhere from the U.S. down to South America and Brazil, sorry, and Australia.
And so, yeah, very proud of what they're doing.
how they're training the next generation, right?
And so some of them now already have students that are faculty members.
Wow.
And so to me, that's the proudest achievement.
Obviously, seeing livestock producers around the world, especially when I travel and they say, you know, we use this system or we use this device that you helped develop.
And it's...
it helped us become more productive.
Those are the things I really get a lot of joy out of.
Um, so from my, in my current role, I think,
the things that are going to be have impact for years to come are some of the infrastructure that i have been able to get built so and i'll give you some examples we just had a ribbon cutting on may 6 of last year so a year ago to open the new reproduction and biotecnology center out at the relis campus
um and so that's it's the only facility of its kind in the world um we have just we had the groundbreaking last week for the new meat sites
So that is something that I've worked on for eight years to get to this point.
It has to feel so good seeing it.
Yeah.
And so to be able to figure out how to come up with $130 million and put all of that together and spend eight years getting to this point, those are things that I think will have impacts for the future.
We did a ribbon cutting for a facility up in Canyon, in the High Plains.
So there are researchers that are going to help
whether it's cattle producers or wheat producers or whatever it is in the High Plains, my hope is that 30 years from now, as a result of having that facility, they generate results that have impacts for the agricultural folks in that region.
Absolutely.
It's absolutely global.
That's what I'm figuring out from you is that one small little thing here can absolutely change the world.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
Wow.
So yeah, so those are the things that I think.
Yeah, absolutely.
Specifically when you became the leader here at the department head, what were some of the goals or visions that you really wanted to bring in with you?
Yeah, so let me talk not so much as department head, but as director of AgroLife Research, right?
I wanted to modernize the agency and modernize internal controls so things that we did internally
that we are using the latest technology so using electronic things using artificial intelligence to make decisions using data to make decisions and we've we've been able to modernize over time my goal was to increase research expenditures
And that's important.
The number itself isn't important, but if we are increasing research expenditures, it means that people who fund the work that we do,
are seeing the importance of the work so that they fund it does that make sense absolutely and so we've been able to increase research expenditures by 53 in four years so that's unheard of 2022 when i started our research expenditures were 225 million this past year they were 345 million
And so it's going after bigger, more complex problems.
If you think back 60, 70, 80 years ago, most of the problems that we had to solve could be solved by individual little things, right?
Right.
I don't know, make a cow herd more productive.
You could do one or two things that we did research on and that would make a significant impact on a cattle operation.
Well, now it's more complex, right?
And so how do we bring disciplines together?
Right.
So if we're trying to solve a cattle problem, it's not just people in the Department of Animal Science, right?
You've got 70% of the cost of a cattle operation of feed.
Feed is going to either be pastures or it's going to be... And so the people who grow that feed and how do you get them involved?
How do you get the health people, the veterinarians involved?
So bringing together, trying to solve problems in a more complex way.
Absolutely.
Does this mean that with every new innovation that the research side of it comes more nuanced?
Is there a correlation there?
Yes.
So you mean the research is more nuanced?
It is because some of the changes we make are so incremental, they don't make a big difference.
But if you want to make big changes,
it has to be a multidisciplinary approach that that has a look at holistically the whole enterprise right yeah um and whether it's i mean it could be water quality that has an impact on on ultimate production of chickens right and but if you're a chicken geneticist
last thing you're thinking about is water right right and it doesn't matter how different the genetics are if the water is not good enough quality right and so how do you bring all those folks together to make big differences that makes sense make make people actually interact with each other yeah so
So, yeah.
The other thing, though, that I think has been really important for me is to focus on improving infrastructure across the state for research infrastructure, which allows people to become more productive.
And when you think of all of our research infrastructure and agriculture across the state, most of that infrastructure was built 50 to 90 years ago.
Wow.
science is very different now technology is very different now so how do we get improved infrastructure with improved analytical techniques right you know it could be lab instrumentation whatever it is drones get that in the hands of people
that then can go and do good work.
And we think that's paying off.
Absolutely.
It sounds like it.
Thinking back through your whole career, what have been some of the biggest challenges that you faced or that your team has faced when you're on teams?
Yeah.
Boy, that's...
That's a really good question.
I think challenges that we have had to overcome
are artificial barriers that people put in front of you right so whether it's a bureaucratic process or a regulatory process or something along those lines that is a barrier for something good to happen right that makes sense and so trying to figure out
creative ways to either get around it or to have conversations with the people that are making those decisions of why their decisions have an impact i would say that's been the biggest barrier um you know i think uh very often too it's the most researchers rely on funding to do the work
and i've been very very fortunate that i've tended to always have a lot of funding but it's sometimes the best work isn't done with the funding you get done right and in other words some of my best research are things that we know is going to make a difference
But you end up having to focus on something because that's what it's being funded.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, the grants.
Yeah, exactly.
And the competitive grant side of things.
You spend so much time trying to focus on funding because that's a metric that you use to run your lab.
But the impact for work very often isn't the work being funded.
Right.
I feel the pain over in the art side of things.
Oh, absolutely.
That's right.
And obviously there's a lot more money in the STEM fields like ours.
Over the course of your career, I know we've kind of touched on this, but over the course of your career, what has teaching meant to you personally?
Teaching, yeah.
I would, you know, for me, I probably lean on this more and say mentoring.
Mentoring.
Right.
You know, I think...
And I let a lot of my students know all the time, and even my own kids, that successful people don't become successful without other people believing in them.
There's not a single person that can say they ended up doing what they were doing without looking back and going, boy, if this person didn't believe in me, I wouldn't have got this job or I wouldn't have got this position.
and it's accepting the fact and being humble enough to accept the fact that you are going to have people believe in you or help you along the way and being comfortable with that I've seen so many bright people over the years that I don't know if it's arrogance I don't know if it is
a lack of self-confidence, whatever it is, where they're not accepting help.
And then 30 years later, they look back and go, geez, I didn't get done what I could have got done because I didn't listen.
I know that is not quite answering the question you asked, but I think, yeah, I think mentoring to me means that
you try and allow people to build on their strengths and understand what their weaknesses are and give them the opportunity to fly.
And so if I focus on graduate students, right, every one of my students has a different skill set or has had a different skill set over the 30 years that I've been a faculty member.
none of them are good at everything, but all of them have some phenomenal strengths.
I can't say I've had a bad graduate student, like a student that I just was like, this is just going to be a disaster, right?
Right.
But it's, so being able to, as a mentor, being able to understand what their strengths are, help them on their weaknesses, and then
provide some mentoring to let them succeed where I think that their best opportunity is.
Does that make sense?
Absolutely, it does.
It honestly sounds like you were built, you were made to be a mentor.
That's the energy I'm getting from you.
Yeah, and I will admit, right, I don't personally, I don't get a lot of
energy or pleasure i enjoy speaking to classes but teaching a class every day some people are just really really good at that that's not me i i love speaking to students anywhere from kindergarten age all the way up
but I don't get a lot of energy, um, teaching a class to career undergraduates or even graduate students where, um, it's a routine every Monday, Wednesday, Friday.
That just, it doesn't excite me.
I just don't get a lot of energy out of it.
I mean, I far prefer to do
a lot more one-on-one mentoring or mentoring a group that's sort of working in a mission.
Right.
And I really take my hat off to those teachers that do a phenomenal job because they're so good at it.
And that's just not my strength.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
As you said, we all can't be good at everything.
Thinking back to your education, is there any professors or mentors that stick out in your mind as
Like, those are the ones.
Yeah, actually, yeah, there is almost every step of the way, right?
I can name one or two people that were, so as an undergraduate student, I have a person whom I still remain in touch with today, who sort of took me under...
his wing and really pushed me, right?
I mean, he didn't just, um, I mean, I was a foreign student just new to this country, didn't know anybody, uh, but really, really pushed me and was somebody who helped me try and figure out where to go next.
My mentor for my Master and PhD was a phenomenal scientist.
And him and I still are very good friends today.
But, you know, we were very, very different in terms of our personalities.
And, you know, I really appreciated the fact that he never,
He never, I mean, yeah, he pushed me too, but never did he question the things that I was doing and the life choices I was making.
Right.
And was always very supportive.
But he was a phenomenal mentor.
Wow.
And probably was the reason I'm still a scientist today.
How fortunate.
Yeah, it is.
So.
Carrying on about the students and mentors, what kind of skills or values that you hope your students carry with them through their careers?
So there are two things that I think are really important for all students, right?
And I see it more and more now.
One is that...
I think that the grit probably is more important than almost anything else, right?
It's the have with it-ness to get through something difficult, right?
Yeah.
And really push yourself.
And it's far more important than getting an A.
It's far more important than being able to graduate with a 4.0.
It's your ability to grit out during tough times and not let it have a negative impact on you.
Use it to learn.
Right.
I think that that's extremely important.
Um, I tell all of my students all the time and my kids are so tired of hearing it that getting a degree is not a degree in wisdom.
It's a degree in perseverance.
And so
You've got to persevere.
There are times that you're going to hate it, and it's how do you get through that without hating it, without hating the process, but knowing there are going to be difficult times before you get to the end.
That makes sense.
So I think, yeah, that's important.
And then having the education...
is to open a door but it doesn't keep the door open right yes everything else about you once you get a job or once you do what you're doing um keep learning keep on uh making sure that you're becoming a better person than you are the day before right yeah um and and so i i tell people that all the time i mean
The job isn't going to keep you there.
At least the degree isn't going to keep you in your job, right?
Right.
It's going to open the door, but it's not going to be the reason you get hired, and it's not going to be the reason you keep your job.
Absolutely.
That's fantastic.
I'm going to take that advice.
So what has it meant to you personally or even professionally to be part of Texas A&M?
Yeah, I mean, I'll start off by saying I'm proud to be part of Texas A&M, right?
It's a phenomenal university.
And you'll probably hear a lot of people talk about the core values.
And I think that that's true.
But I think what makes me proud is the type of people
that come here as students and as faculty members and staff, for the most part, are good people, right?
I agree.
So, yeah, they want the best for themselves, for their students, and they're just very, very good people.
Now, beyond that, what I'm proud about is that almost any time you say,
you're from texas a m in some way however you that comes into discussion very seldom do you does it come with a negative connotation right so it's what the people have done before we've been here to have built something fairly strong right that has given it a reputation to have grown good people that have gone out and made a difference
And so I guess that's what I think about it.
I'm proud.
I tell people all the time how lucky we are to be a part of Texas A&M.
I feel the same.
So switching over topics a little bit.
Sure.
How has the field of animal science and specifically reproduction processes changed since your career?
Yeah.
I think animal science in general has significantly changed.
I mean, in terms of reproduction, I think we have so many more tools now than what we did when my career started 30 years ago.
One of the things that I think is quite amazing in all of this
is when you're doing the work when we're doing the research and so on you don't really notice change as much but you know i'm starting to get to a stage in my career now where i'm being asked to talk about progress and change and you know when i give those talks now i'm like
oh boy look what has been happening over the last 30 years look at the change but yeah so animal production is very different when I started 30 years ago the average livestock producer could survive by not implementing technology and implementing
genetic selection and implementing things like this the average livestock producer today cannot afford not to do that cannot afford to not implement modern technology right okay and so what you're seeing now is the average farmer still or rancher is still in the high 50s or low 60s
But you're seeing a brand new generation of people that are coming in and entering animal science that have this expertise in technology.
They're bringing it into the operations and operations are starting to adopt it at a faster and faster rate.
That's so fascinating.
I don't even know if this has an answer, but from an outsider, I was wondering, is there an ideal cattle industry?
And if there is, what would that look like?
That's a good question.
I don't know if there's an ideal cattle industry.
I think...
I'm just thinking, you know, and the reason is that I think there's no ideal cattle industry is not only, I mean, there might be an ideal way to raise cattle today and meet certain markets that works for you today.
Okay, yeah.
but tomorrow the world around that industry is that that operation is different that they have to adapt that makes sense does that right okay and so i'll explain uh how i mean this take a look at how the consumer has changed in their perception of beef okay in the 80s and 90s people love beef right we ate a lot of beef
and so the cattle industry then was just producing beef and it wasn't necessarily the highest quality beef people just loved it but the eating experience was variable you could go to the store and you could buy a steak and go and cook it and sometimes you'd like it and sometimes you wouldn't right yeah because you might not have prepared it well the product might not have been very good right the the industry in the u.s
really changed and they started improving the quality right and so producers who might have been able to fit that market and at that time now have to adjust their genetics because the industry demanded it but then the consumer had also got into a situation where red meat is bad for you fat is bad for you so
um so the cattle industry is changing and adjusting to that and now we're in a situation where thank goodness people have started actually seeing the science and it's not necessarily the red meat it's the carbohydrates it's bread and sugar and things right uh where protein animal protein actually has a lot of really good benefits right
And so now we're in a market where marbling in cattle is extremely important.
Marbling is the intramuscular fat that actually helps us have more tender products.
Oh, like Wagyu and stuff like that.
Yeah, exactly.
Wagyu and then most Angus genetics products.
And so when people cook that meat, it's more difficult to screw it up.
I see.
so they have a better eating experience right and and now we also have um people that make more money and are willing to pay more for their for better quality beef right so the producers that are not have not started producing animals that have better genetics the cattle markets have now shifted that were in the 80s and 90s
It didn't matter what size animal went through the sale barn to slaughter, every animal was worth the same price based on weight.
That's not the case anymore.
An animal that was really good at marbling genetics is worth about $1,000 more than an animal that isn't, right?
so can you imagine being a producer that was producing poor quality beef that in the 80s and 90s might have been doing a good job so they didn't adjust so it's really difficult to pinpoint what the ideal operation is and every country has a different system that makes sense but at the same time I think the ideal operation is the operation that is willing to adjust to what the consumer wants
Perfect.
I didn't think that was ever going to have an answer because it's too complicated.
But I think you put that very well.
Yeah.
Are there any, I know we talked about technology and changes in the way you've approached things, but is there something that really excites you now that you see coming into the future?
Any technologies or process?
Yeah.
Yeah, I think we touched on this a little bit, but I do think what really excites me right now is I think we're starting to see that people value where their food comes from.
And then coupled with that is the exponential increase in our ability to use data to make decisions and decision aid tools and tools.
So AI, machine learning, sensor technology, and then a consumer starting to value where the food comes from.
I think those two.
And these last couple questions are like personal reflections kind of questions.
Has there been any turning points in your career, whether that's good or bad, that significantly changed the trajectory of your life or career in general?
Yeah, so, yeah, multiple, right?
I think...
And this might be something, you know, back to the mentoring.
One of the things I tell my students all the time when they're trying to make decisions is, is it the right decision?
It's not really the right decision.
When you think it's Yogi Berra said, when you come to a fork in the road, take it.
Right?
So you're going to come to multiple times in your life where you have decisions to make.
Don't sit there and pine over the decision.
Make the decision and don't look back.
Right.
So in my life, I mean, I think the decision.
at a very young age not knowing anybody in the u.s and coming to study as a teenager to leave a family in africa right right um and not knowing what the future held but that my plan was always to go back so that was one i think um not necessarily having uh the opportunity to go back to africa was a big
turning point in my career and don't regret it at all.
I'm just sad when it happened but I think I've been able to have a larger impact even on my home country doing what I'm doing than had I gone back.
That's got to feel good.
Yeah, that does.
And then probably the last really big decision was
i never really thought of being a university administrator right um never crossed my mind it was never something that i aspired to do but taking the leap when somebody asked me if i would consider it i think has been has been life-changing and
I look back at it now and every administrative position I've had, I've been able to have a positive impact on more and more people.
And so those are probably the big ones.
Absolutely.
You've already given some advice, but is there any other kind of advice that you would like to give to people who maybe are interested in this field or just interested in this field?
Yeah, I think there is some advice, right?
I think the folks that will make the biggest impact in the future
In my field, and I'll just talk about animal science in general, and maybe even over the entire AgriLife research, right?
The thing that I would say are those that are going to be the most successful are going to be people who are willing to adapt faster.
And I'll give you an example.
in the past if we were going to look for a faculty member or look for somebody to lead a certain area we would look we would say well we need somebody who's a geneticist right and then we go out and look for somebody who fits a position description
But now when we do that, yeah, we may broadly want a geneticist, but really what we want is we want somebody who over the next 30 to 40 years is going to be able to adapt to needs over that period of time.
Because if we hire a geneticist today,
30 years from now genetics may not be the focus that we need right we need somebody who's willing to adapt as time changes so i think adaptability is extremely important for anybody for young people i would say
most of them want to come out and make a lot of money right off the bat almost everybody wants to do that and i would let everybody know to be patient right make sure that you spend your first five or ten years out of school honing your skills you may not it may not be the most the greatest income generator you may not become a millionaire in your first five or ten years but build
on that and then gradually grow through the system and and and take on opportunities yeah don't rush it yeah
I think we have too many people that want to leave and go and start a job right away because they see the dollar signs, but they don't see the investments in themselves.
Right.
That's fantastic.
I have two legacy questions from, they've been asked for the last 50 years in these oral histories.
The first is, if you were given a million dollars and you had to use it somehow on this university, does it matter where or when, just your pick, what would you put that to?
If I had a million dollars, I would probably put it into an endowment so that it would live forever and use the interest from that to focus on graduate education.
Fantastic.
First person who says that to me, by the way.
First person who's told me that.
Oh, really?
Yeah, that's, yeah.
It's a unique answer.
And my very last question is, how do you want to be remembered in your career or personal life?
That's a good question.
I don't know.
I haven't really thought about how I want to be remembered.
My hope is that when I hang up my shoes and I'm six feet under, that people will remember me for having an impact on other people's lives.
I think the accolades in terms of science and things like that, I think those are great, but I think that's not really what drives me.
And I really want them to remember that I was hugely passionate about agriculture.
Absolutely.
This is the first time I've physically met you in the flesh, and I can even feel that.
So I'm sure that's going to be it.
It's going to be your legacy.
Yeah.
Is there any questions or comments that you wanted to...
Wanted to talk about that?
Yeah, I think so.
Thank you so much for doing this, by the way.
Oh, anytime.
If you need more, let me know.
Absolutely.